New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Station and Structure Drawings Collection 1991.0138
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Station and Structure Drawings Collection
1887-1993
1991.0138
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
26.0 Linear feet
The collection consists of 303 architectural drawings of 39 railroad stations, engine houses, signal stations and towers, and auxiliary buildings built by the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad from 1886 to 1964. The maps are organized by job number; following the description of each plan is its print number. Two of the stations were designed by prominent architects Henry Bacon and Cass Gilbert. The collection also includes one gate sign, ca. 1920s, from Back Bay Station in Massachusetts.
26 linear feet.
New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad.
History
For almost one hundred years the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, better known as the New Haven Railroad, was the primary means of passenger and freight transportation in southern New England. Chartered in 1872, this merger between the New York & New Haven and Hartford & New Haven railroads later included the long desired rail link between Boston and New York. Approximately one hundred small independent railroads were built in southern New England between 1826 and the 1880s. By 1904, the majority were absorbed into the vast New Haven system. At its peak in 1929, the New Haven Railroad owned and operated 2,131 miles of track throughout eastern New York, Connecticut, Massachusetts, and Rhode Island.
The local railroad lines that eventually became part of the New Haven system developed in response to local business and transportation needs. Unlike the Western states, where railroads preceded and shaped settlement, in the Northeast they served primarily to link existing towns, businesses, and markets. The New Haven system thus developed as a result of numerous consolidations and mergers. The New Haven traced its founding to 1826, when one of its predecessor companies originated, but the New York, New Haven and Hartford Railroad was not chartered until 1872. The company followed the pattern of consolidation established by the Pennsylvania Railroad and other companies, particularly after 1889, when major lines in Connecticut, Rhode Island, and southern Massachusetts provided a strong network linking New York and Boston. By 1890, company revenue exceeded $100,000,000 per year, and the New Haven employed 4,000 people to serve twelve million passengers annually.
This success led a wealthy group of New York investors, headed by J. P. Morgan, to seek and gain control of the New Haven's board. In 1903, Morgan installed Charles Mellen as president of the railroad. Together Morgan and Mellen set out to achieve a complete monopoly of transportation in New England. Substantial improvements to the system were made during the Mellen years, including electrification of rail lines between Woodlawn, New York, and New Haven, Connecticut, and construction of a power generating plant in Cos Cob, Connecticut. These accomplishments, however, were overshadowed by Morgan's ambitious schemes to dominate all modes of transportation in New England. Steamboat lines, trolley companies, and other railroad lines were purchased regardless of price and incorporated into the New Haven system.
An investigation of the New Haven's activities by Louis Brandeis in 1907 revealed the overextended railroad was on the verge of financial collapse. Morgan's death in 1913 and Mellen's subsequent resignation brought to a close a stormy period in the New Haven's history.
During the First World War, all of the railroads in the United States, including the New Haven Railroad, were operated by the federal government. After the war, under Edward Pearson, President through 1928, the railroad was able to recover partially, despite increasing competition from automobiles, by sharing in the national economic growth of the 1920s. The company tried to meet this transportation competition by forming the New England Transportation Company, which operated a fleet of trucks and buses. Recovery of the New Haven, however, was cut short by the Depression of the 1930s, and in 1935 the New Haven plunged into bankruptcy. The company remained in trusteeship until 1947, when it returned to private ownership.
A series of struggles for control of the company in the post World War II period severely weakened the management of the company and its ability to adapt to changes in the transportation industry. The completion of the Connecticut Turnpike and other superhighways and the start of air shuttle service between Boston and New York intensified competition. The company's historic liability as a railroad overburdened with many short, costly branch lines further accelerated its decline.
On 7 July 1961, the New Haven Railroad once again went into receivership. A seven year trusteeship period followed, culminating in the absorption of the New Haven in the Penn Central system on 1 January 1969. Three years later the Penn Central itself collapsed into bankruptcy. The former components of the New Haven Railroad were divided among several entities. Freight service was assumed by Conrail when it was formed in 1976, although the Providence & Worcester also provided freight service on portions of the former New Haven, as did a few other operators. Passenger commuter service was funded by the New York Metropolitan Transit Authority and the Connecticut Department of Transportation. Long-haul passenger service was provided by Amtrak beginning in 1971. After 1976 passenger commuter service was operated by Conrail. In 1982, the United States Congress passed legislation that forced Conrail to divest itself of its commuter rail lines. On 1 January 1983, Metro-North Commuter Railroad, under joint ownership of the states of New York and Connecticut, took over all commuter passenger service. Amtrak continued to handle all long-haul passenger service.
The history of the New Haven Railroad reveals a company formed by one of the classic merger and consolidation patterns of the late 19th century, which was later unable to respond effectively to major changes in the transportation industry. The company's rapid growth, collapse, temporary recovery, and final dissolution offer a dramatic story, with government regulation, internal management decisions, and market competition playing important roles in the company's history.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of 303 architectural drawings of 39 railroad stations, engine houses, signal stations and towers, and auxiliary buildings built by the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad and its successors from 1886 to 1964.
Arrangement
The architectural drawings are organized by the job number given to the station or structure by the railroad company, and thereunder by the sheet number. Researchers should request the drawings by their folder number, the name of the station, the job number, and the print number.
Series I: Station and Structure Drawings, ( 1886-1993 )
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to New England railroads, particularly the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Bacon, Henry.; Gilbert, Cass, 1859-1934.; Towner, William Thomas.; Drawings.; Railroad stations -- Connecticut.; Railroad stations -- Massachusetts.; Railroad stations -- Rhode Island.; Railroad stations--New York (State)
- Series I: Station and Structure Drawings, 1886-1984
  - #3016 Larchmont, New York, Railroad Station, 1887-1889 (Folder 1)
    - Cover shed 012494
    - Roof plan 012495
    - Top of column for arcade at Branford 012496
    - Detail of inside finish of arched window 012497
    - Plan of seats 012498
    - Proposed canopy over stairs 012499
    - Front elevation 012500
    - Detail of window doots and wainscot 012501
    - Extension and change of roof 012502
    - Various sections, elevations, and details 012503
    - Floor plan 012504
    - Platform landing and stairway 012505
    - Change of roof 012506
    - Check window 012507
    - Location of pipe 012508
    - Transverse section, elevation of door, windows, and mantel 012509
    - West elevation 012510
    - Cellar and foundation 012511
    - Baggage room floor 012512
    - Details of Platform cover 012513
    - Arcade 012514
    - Cross girder 012515
    - Details of column 012516
    - Plan of main floor 012517
    - Design and details platform 012518
  - #3027 New Rochelle, New York, Railroad Station Cover Shed and Baggage Room, 1892-1894 (Folder 2)
    - Cover shed on top of wall 012253
    - Cover shed and baggage room 012254
    - Cover shed 012255
    - Elevation 012256
    - Plan 012257
    - Cover shed, waiting and baggage rooms 012258
  - #3103 Branford, Connecticut, Passenger Station, 1886 (Folder 3)
    - Elevation of mantel 011648
    - Elevation of door casings 011649
    - Elevation of window casings 011650
    - Ceiling in waiting room 011651
    - Terracotta finish in waiting room and ticket office 011652
    - Elevation and Plan 011653 Ticket office window 011654
    - Longitudinal section 011655
    - Plan for Terracotta finish 016656
    - Transverse of platform 011657
    - Lintels, sills and courses 011658
    - Plan 011659
    - Details of work 011660
    - Passenger station 011661
  - #3110 Lyme, Connecticut, Passenger Station, 1906 (Folder 4)
    - Foundation 012134
    - Elevations 012135
    - Site plan and elevations 012136
    - Details 012137
  - #3177 Hartford, Connecticut, Passenger Station, 1903 (Folder 4)
    - Track elevations 02064
    - Asylum Street Elevation 020643
    - Turnstile gate 020644
    - Transverse section through general waiting area 020646
    - First floor 020647
    - Second floor 020648
  - #3242 Naugatuck, Connecticut, Passenger Station, [Drawings by architect Henry Bacon noted with a *], 1907-1908 (Folder 5)
    - Electric lighting 011578
    - Electric lighting, first floor 011579
    - Elevations 011580
    - Site plan 011581*
    - Basement plan 011582*
    - First floor plan 011583*
    - Track and street elevations 011584*
    - Section details 011585*
    - Roof framing 011586*
    - Elevations of mantel, drinking fountain and seats in waiting room 011587*
    - Smoking room 011588*
    - Basement lighting 011589
    - Site plan lighting 011590
    - Transverse section 011591*
    - Sections and elevations 011592*
    - Electric lighting, first floor 011593
    - Foundation plan 011594
    - Women's toilet room 011595*
    - Women's retiring room 011596*
    - Men's toilet room 011597*
    - Ticket office details 011598*
    - Waiting room 011599*
    - Clock, roof and rafters 011600*
  - #3249 Naugatuck, Connecticut, Railway Station, 1889 (Folder 5)
    - Section of platform 012138
    - Location 012139
    - Elevations 012140
    - Floor and foundation plan 012141
    - Framing plan of roof 012142
    - Details 012143
  - #3272 Forest Hills, Massachusetts, Passenger Station, 1896 (Folder 6)
    - Elevations and details 012245
    - Details of windows 012246
    - North bound station 012247
    - Elevations 012248
    - Floor plan, northbound station 012249
    - Location, site plan 012250
    - Elevations 012251
    - South bound station 012252
  - #3330 Norwood Central, Massachusetts, Station ( New England Railroad Company), 1898 (Folder 7)
    - Elevation 020695
  - #3370 Hyannis, Massachusetts, Passenger Station, 1899, 1943 (Folder 7)
    - Elevation 020327
    - Freight house 020328
    - Site plan 020329
    - Shelter shed, platform and freight house 020330
    - Site plan 020331
    - Waiting room plan 020332
    - Second floor 020333
    - Alterations and additions 020334
  - #3457 Bartow (City Island), New York, Station [Drawings by architect Cass Gilbert noted with a *], 1907, 1910 (Folder 7)
    - Site plan 012170*
    - Mechanical equipment 012171*
    - First floor 012172*
    - Scale details 012173*
    - Scale details 012174*
    - Scale details of shelters 012175*
    - Basement floor plan 012176*
    - First floor plan 012177*
    - East (street) elevation 012178*
    - West (track) elevation 012179*
    - End and cross section 012180*
    - Longitudinal sections 012181*
    - Lighting circuits 012182
    - Basement floor plan 012183
    - First floor plan 012184
    - Stairway 012185
    - Stairway 012186
    - Stairway 012187
    - Coversheds and platforms 012188
  - #3501 Plymouth, Massachusetts, Station [Drawings by architect William Thomas Towner noted with a *], undated (Folder 7)
    - Basement 020314*
    - First floor 020315*
    - Framing 020316*
    - Elevation 020317*
    - Side elevations 020318*
    - Rear elevations 020319*
    - Scale details of front elevation 020320*
    - Scale details 020321*
    - Details 020322*
    - Ticket office 020323*
    - Train shed 020324*
    - Fireplace 020325*
    - Floor plan 020326
  - #3537 Southbridge, Massachusetts, Passenger Station, 1910 (Folder 7)
    - Elevations 020370
    - Foundation plan 020371
    - Ground floor 020372
    - Roof 020373
    - Track elevation 020374
    - Transverse/longitudinal sections 020375
    - Scale details 020376
    - Hot water heating 020377
    - Site plan 020378
    - Site plan 020379
    - Drains 020380
    - Manhole and catch basins 020381
  - #3543 Foxboro, Massachusetts, Passenger Station, 1910 (Folder 8)
    - Foundation plan 020345
    - Ground floor 020346
    - Elevation and sections 020347
    - Elevation 020348
    - Scale details 020349
  - #3593 Buzzard's Bay, Massachusetts, Signal Tower, 1911 (Folder 8)
    - General plan 020350
    - Elevation 020351
    - Elevation 020352
    - Section 020353
    - Section details 020354
    - Section details 020355
  - #3711 Bridgewater, Massachusetts, Station, 1893-1894, 1900 (Folder 8)
    - Elevation of street front 019972
    - Elevations 019973
    - Elevations 019974
    - Cross section 019975
    - Floor plan 019976
  - #3713 Canton Junction, Massachusetts, Station, 1901 (Folder 8)
    - Waiting room elevation 016635
  - #3756 Great Barrington, Massachusetts, Passenger Station, 1900 (Folder 8)
    - Foundation plan 011642
    - Floor plan 011643
    - Elevation and cross section track front 011644
    - Street front elevation 011645
    - Details 011646
    - Elevation of ticket office 011647
  - #3807 South Boston, Massachusetts, Commissary Building, Dover Street Yard, 1915 (Folder 9)
    - Foundation 016636
    - First floor 016637
    - Second floor 016638
    - Elevation 016639
  - #3819 West Haven, Connecticut, Passenger Station, 1915 (Folder 9)
    - Elevations and cross sections, East bound 016932
    - Elevations and cross sections, West bound 016933
  - #3823 Pocasset, Massachusetts, Passenger Station, 1915 (Folder 9)
    - Foundation 020308
    - Ground floor 020309
    - Roof plan 020310
    - Elevation 020311
    - Section 020312
    - Scale details 020313
  - #3836 Providence, Rhode Island, Engine Facilities at Charles and Oregon Streets, 1916 (Folder 10)
    - Brick store house 017001
    - Ground floor 017002
    - Stalls 017003
    - Foundation and ground floor 017004
    - Elevations 017005
    - Cross section and detail elevation 017006
    - Lighting plan 017007
    - Ground floor plans 017008
    - Dry Sand Storage Tower 017009
    - Sand house 017010
    - Sand screen 017011
    - Detail of post and beam connections 017012
    - Brick storehouse adjoining engine house 017013
    - Extension of roof 017014
    - Turntable and train shed 017015
  - #3913 South Boston, Massachusetts, Signal Station at First Street, 1918 (Folder 11)
    - Site plan 016645
    - Elevations 016646
    - Elevations 016647
    - Sections 016648
    - Scale details 016649
  - #3917 Cedar Hill, New Haven, Connecticut, Division Office Building (not constructed), 1918 (Folder 11)
    - Ground floor 016960
    - Second floor 016961
    - Elevations 016962
    - Elevation 016963
    - Ground floor 016964
    - Second floor 016965
    - Details 016966
    - Details 016967
    - Details 016968
  - #3919 State Line, Massachusetts, Engine Facilities, 1918 (Folder 12)
    - Cross sections 020392
    - Details and plans 020393
    - Elevations and sections 020394
    - Piping, heating, lighting and details 020395
  - #3921 Springfield, Massachusetts, Engine Facilities, 1918, 1923 (Folder 12)
    - Floor plan and elevation 020404
    - Roof plan 020405
    - Section plan 020406
    - Plans and elevations 020407
    - Steam, water, air and fire lines 020408
    - Heating and lighting plan 020409
    - Lighting layout 020410
    - Glass Block panels 020411
  - #3960 Boston, Massachusetts, Southampton Street Station Engine Terminal, 1916 (Folder 13)
    - Elevations and wall sections 016686
    - Ground floor 016688
    - Cross section 016689
    - Details and wall sections 016691
    - Roof plan 016692
    - Roof framing plan 016693
    - Ground floor plan 016695
    - General plan 016705
  - #3990 Providence, Rhode Island, Oregon Street Engine Tools and Oil Storage Building, 1918 (Folder 13)
    - Sections 016999
  - #4014 Providence, Rhode Island, Building for Engine Men, 1918 (Folder 13)
    - Elevations 017397
    - Foundation plan 017398
  - #4386 Springfield, Massachusetts, Proposed Signal Tower, 1927 (Folder 13)
    - Floor plans 020655
    - Elevations 020656
    - Sections and elevations 020657
    - Details 020658
  - #4430 Providence, Rhode Island, Passenger Station, Proposed Canopies over Sidewalk, 1928 (Folder 14)
    - Canopies over sidewalk 020651
  - #4634 Quincy, Massachusetts, Passenger Station, 1931, 1942 (Folder 14)
    - Elevation and details 020073
    - Elevations and cross sections 020074
    - North bound subway stairs 020075
    - South bound subway stairs 020076
    - General lighting plan 020077
    - Ticket office 020078
  - #4764 Sharon, Massachusetts, Station, 1937 (Folder 14)
    - Cross sections 020018
    - Site plan 020019
    - Elevations and sections 020020
    - Detail and elevations 020021
    - Heating and lighting layout and details 020022
  - #5689 Dedham, Massachusetts, Route 128 Station and Shelter, 1963-1964 (Folder 15)
    - Tabulation of bids 019758
    - Sanitary drainage 019759
    - Ticket window jamb 019760
    - Site plan 019761
    - Elevations 019762
    - Floor plans and sections 019763
    - Elevation revisions 019764
    - Sections and details 019765
    - Plumbing plan 019766
    - Floor plans 019767
    - Sections 019768
    - Floor plans 019769
    - Plan of canopy 019770
    - Detail brick courses 019771
    - Proposed station and shelter 019772
  - #14056 Cedar Hill, New Haven, Connecticut, Engine House facilities, 1911 (Folder 16)
    - Grating for ash pits 024002
    - Handle for turntable 024003
    - Changes to pit #10 024004
    - Cast iron grating 024005
    - Soil test frame 024006
    - Locomotive door 024007
    - Power house engines and generators 024008
    - Power house 024009
    - Bridge to carry pipes 024010
    - Water tank support 024011
    - Water tank support 024012
    - Pipe layout 024013
    - House for sand drier 024014
    - Pipe connections 024015
    - Shop details 024016
    - Coal conveyor 024017
    - Hose houses 024018
    - Storage bin for wet sand 024019
    - Plank walk over heat duct 024021
    - Concrete catch basins 024022
    - Pits for water columns 024023
    - Progress chart/Auxiliary buildings 024024
  - #16624 Newport, Rhode Island, Proposed Freight House and Passenger Station, 1900 (Folder 17)
    - Pier and fender for end of long wharf 024096
    - Site plan 024097
    - Passenger station elevations 024098
    - Freight house 024099
    - Passenger station 024100
    - Station floor plans 024101
    - Freight house elevations 024102
    - Passenger station details 024103
    - Freight house ground plan 024104
  - Bridgeport, Connecticut, Old Railroad Station, Victor Christ Janer & Do Chung Associates; these drawings are photocopies of and courtesy of the City of Bridgeport Department of Archives & Records, 1974 (Folder 17)
    - Site plan -- platform level
    - Site plan -- street level
    - Basement plan
    - Platform level plan
    - Second level plan
    - Building elevations
    - Elevation and section
  - Back Bay Station, Gate Sign, ca. 1920s (Folder 18)
  - Boston Terminal Company, South Station, ca. 1898-1956 (Folder 19)
    - Boston Terminal Company, Southern Station, Portion of Second Floor Plan, Shepley Rutan and Coolidge Architects. Three copies, one of which is very deteriorated and cannot be copied, [rolled], ca. 1898
    - Boston Terminal Company, Basement Plan, South Station, Boston, Massachusetts, 1931 July 30
    - The Boston Terminal Company, General Plan of Terminal Station at Boston, Massachusetts, for the NYNH&H and B&A Railroads. Too large and deteriorated for copying, must be handled with care, rolled, 1944 May
    - South Station, Boston, Massachusetts, Station Track Requirement for Through Service Based on Trains of Sunday, 1946 September 22
    - Boston Terminal Company, Plan of Concourse – Waiting Room and Adjacent Areas, 1948 December
    - Proposed Alteration to Shoe Store, South Station [Concourse], Boston, Massachusetts, drawing no. 2, Joseph V. Nuccio, Architectural Designer., 1956 March 28
  - City of Danbury, Connecticut, Union Station Restoration, 120 White Street, 1903, 1993 (Folder 17)
    - 1903 1st Floor Plan
    - Existing 1st Floor Plan, 1993 August 13
  - Waterbury, Connecticut, passenger station, street elevation (photocopy), 1907 (Folder 17)